Finding Aid for William D. Ford Papers 1955-1995
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Legislative Files 1965-1980, 17 linear feet
  - 1979-1980
    - Banking, Finance and Urban Affairs Committee (Box 94)
    - Budget Committee (Box 94)
    - Education and Labor Committee (Box 94)
    - House Administration Committee (Box 94)
    - Interior and Insular Affairs Committee (Box 94)
    - Interstate and Foreign Affairs Committee (Box 94)
    - Judiciary Committee (Box 94)
    - Merchant Marine and Fisheries (Box 94)
    - Post Office and Civil Service Committee (Box 94)
    - Veterans Affairs Committee (Box 94)
    - Voting Records [1979-1984] (Box 94)
    - Ways and Means Committee (Box 94)
- Committee Files 1969-1994, 30 linear feet
  Committee Files (30 linear feet; 1969-1994) are divided into four subseries: Education and Labor Committee; Elementary, Secondary and Vocational Education Subcommittee; Post Office and Civil Service Committee [POCS]; and Staff Files: Ross Eisenbrey. This series documents Ford's legislative responsibilities on the two House committees with which he was most actively involved. Bills, correspondence, briefing notes and memoranda provide a sense of his working relationships with colleagues, committee staff, and lobbyists. Ford's increasingly influential standing on these committees is reflected in the greater size and substance of the committee files in the 1990s, particularly once he became chairman of the Education and Labor committee. The bulk of information about Ford's role in legislating student aid programs is in the Post-Secondary Education Subcommittee files [boxes 116-119].
  Ross Eisenbrey was Ford's senior legislative aide between 1979 and 1988. His files include correspondence and briefing notes pertaining to the Education and Labor and POCS committees, and have been maintained as a separate subseries.
  - Education and Labor Committee
    - Topical
      - 1969 (Box 95)
      - 1970-1971 (Box 95)
      - 1973-1974, 6 folders
        (files relate to H.R. 69, The Elementary and Secondary Education Amendments of 1973)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 151)
        - 1973-1974 (Box 152)
          (continued)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 95)
      - 1975-1976 (Box 96)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 97)
      - 1982 [Education] (Box 97)
      - 1982 [Education], cont. (Box 98)
      - 1983-1988 (Box 98)
      - 1983-1988 cont. (Box 99)
      - 1990-1994 (Box 100)
      - 1990-1994 cont. (Box 101)
    - Miscellaneous files
      - Floor Statements and Extensions of Remarks 1990-1994 (Box 101)
      - Memos from Committee Staff 1990-1994 (Box 101)
      - Michigan-related material 1990-1994 (Box 102)
      - Speeches 1990-1994 (Box 103)
      - Testimony 1990-1994 (Box 103)
      - Topical Briefing Notes and Correspondence 1990-1994 (Box 103)
    - Mass Mailings 1991-1994
      - NAFTA [North American Free Trade Act] (Box 103)
      - Labor-Management Relations Issues (Box 104)
      - Subcommittee Mail (Box 104)
      - Subcommittee Mail, cont. (Box 105)
      - Various Labor Issues (Box 105)
      - Various Labor Issues, cont. (Box 106)
      - Various Labor Issues, cont. (Box 107)
      - Various Labor Issues, cont. (Box 108)
      - Health Care Mailings (Box 108)
      - Health Care Mailings, cont. (Box 109)
  - Elementary, Secondary, and Vocational Educational Subcommittee
    - 1991
      - Chronological File, January-April (Box 109)
      - Chronological File, May-December (Box 110)
      - Topical Files (Box 111)
    - 1992
      - Chronological File, January-May (Box 111)
      - Chronological File, June-December (Box 112)
      - Topical Files, A-D (Box 112)
      - Topical Files, G-S (Box 113)
    - 1993
      - Chronological File, January-May (Box 113)
      - Chronological File, June-December (Box 114)
      - Topical File (Box 115)
    - 1994
      - Chronological File, January-August (Box 115)
      - Chronological File, September-December (Box 116)
      - Topical File (Box 116)
  - Post-Secondary Education Subcommittee
    - 1977-1978
      - Topical File A-B (Box 116)
      - Topical File D-U (Box 117)
      - Topical File V-W (Box 118)
    - 1983-1994
      - Correspondence with Members of Congress (Box 118)
      - Correspondence Regarding Student Aid (Box 119)
      - Education Conferences 1983-1989 (Box 119)
      - Education Conferences 1990-1991 (Box 120)
      - University of Michigan/Veterans Administration Hospital (Box 120)
  - Post Office and Civil Service Committee [POCS]
    - Chronological Files
      - 1975-1976 (Box 120)
      - 1977-1978 (Box 120)
    - President's Private Sector Survey on Cost Control
      - [The Grace Commission] 1982-1983 (Box 121)
  - Staff Files: Ross Eisenbrey
    - 1979-1981
      - POCS correspondence and memos (Box 121)
      - POCS correspondence and memos, cont. (Box 122)
      - Education and Labor Committee correspondence and memos (Box 122)
      - Education and Labor Committee correspondence and memos, cont. (Box 123)
    - 1981-1985
      - Legislative and Subcommittee Topical Files (Box 123)
      - Legislative and Subcommittee Topical Files, cont. (Box 124)
    - 1982-1988 [bulk: 1987-1988]
      - Education and Labor Committee correspondence and memos (Box 124)
      - Education and Labor Committee correspondence and memos, cont. (Box 125)
- Campaign Files 1962-1990, 6 linear feet
  CAMPAIGN MATERIAL (6 linear feet; 1962-1990) contains correspondence, press releases, fliers and memoranda for each of Ford's election campaigns, from his run for Michigan State Senate in 1962 to his 1990 congressional campaign. The series documents the increasing sophistication of both campaigning and fundraising methods from the 1960s to the 1990s.
  Of particular interest is "A Survey of Voter Attitudes in the Fifteenth Congressional District of Michigan", commissioned by Ford in 1980 as an analysis the "Reagan Democrat" phenomenon in the district [box 127].
  Another significant part of the series are the Gerald Carlson Information files [box 132]. Carlson was a "white rights" candidate with connections to the American Nazi Party, who ran against Ford in the early 1980s. Ford's staff collected political material and information about Carlson, as well as tapes of his radio advertisements.
  - Michigan State Senate Campaign 1962
    - Campaign material 1962 (Box 126)
  - Congressional Campaigns
    - 1964 (Box 126)
    - 1966 (Box 126)
    - 1968 (Box 126)
    - 1970 (Box 127)
    - 1972 (Box 127)
    - 1974 (Box 127)
    - 1976 (Box 127)
    - 1978 (Box 127)
    - 1980
      - "A Survey of Voter Attitudes in the Fifteenth Congressional District of Michigan" June 1980 (Box 127)
    - 1982 (Box 127)
    - 1982 (cont.) (Box 128)
    - 1984 (Box 128)
    - 1984 cont. (Box 129)
    - 1985 [fundraising] (Box 129)
    - 1985 [fundraising], cont. (Box 130)
    - 1986 (Box 130)
    - 1988 (Box 131)
    - 1990 (Box 131)
    - 1990 cont. (Box 132)
  - Gerald Carlson Information Files
    - 1980-1986 (includes audiotapes and cassettes) (Box 132)
- Public Relations 1960-1992, 10 linear feet
  PUBLIC RELATIONS (10 linear feet; 1960-1992) includes speech materials, press releases, newsclippings, and schedules. Box 140 contains some biographical pieces and articles about Ford.
  - Michigan State Senate Activities
    - 1960-1965 (Box 133)
  - Speeches
    - 1965-1973 (Box 133)
    - 1974-May 1986 (Box 134)
    - June 1986-April 1991 (Box 135)
    - May 1991-December 1991 (Box 136)
  - Press Material
    - Press Releases 1964-1981 (Box 136)
    - Press Logs May 1989-May 1993 (Box 137)
    - Congressional Record Inserts and Bills Introduced
      - 1967-1968 (Box 138)
      - 1970-1972 (Box 138)
      - 1973-1976 (Box 139)
    - Selected remarks and statements (from) Congressional Record (Box 150)
      - 1969-1970 (Box 150)
        (from 1997 accession)
    - Daily Schedules 1968-1969, 1982-1991 (Box 140)
    - District Office Reports 1965-1971 (Box 140)
    - Biographies, Newsclippings and Publicity 1964-1992 (Box 140)
  - VIP Scrapbooks
    - 1968-1975 (Box 141)
    - 1976-1983 (Box 142)
- Visual Material, 1955-1994, 7 linear feet
  VISUAL MATERIAL (7 linear feet; 1955-1994) consists of photographs and videotapes. Photographs are arranged in chronological order, and include pictures of virtually all the major events of Ford's political career. there are photographs of Ford campaigning, at bill signings, with political personalities, receiving awards and honorary degrees, presiding at Congressional committee meetings, and speaking with constituents. The bulk of the collection date from Ford's tenure in Congress (1964-1994); a smaller portion date from his service as justice of the peace and as Michigan state senator. There are also photographs of Ford with state and national political figures.
  - Photographs, 1955-1994, 7 linear feet
    - Portraits (Box 143)
    - Autographed portraits of public figures (Box 143)
      (mainly Michigan's congressional delegation)
    - Staff (with WDF) (Box 143)
    - WDF as child (Box 143)
    - WDF's grandparents' 50th anniversary (Box 143)
    - WDF as justice of the peace, 1955-1956 and before (1953-1954?), with G. Mennen Williams circa 1953-1956 (Box 143)
    - Undated
      - WDF (informal poses) and with other public figures, including Cesar Chavez, Menachem Begin, Thomas P. O'Neill, and Zolton Ferency) (Box 143)
    - 1962
      - WDF with John Swainson (Box 143)
    - 1963
      - WDF with Robert F. Kennedy circa 1963 (Box 143)
      - WDF with T. John Lesinski (Box 143)
      - WDF with son as member of Michigan's Constitutional Convention and with group holding placards supporting passage of the constitution (Box 143)
    - 1964
      - WDF at State Senate functions (Box 143)
      - Campaign photos, 2 envelopes (Box 143)
        include photos of Lyndon Johnson, Hubert Humphrey, Walter Reuther, and others
      - Campaigning with Senator Philip Hart and others (Box 143)
    - 1965
      - WDF with Carl Albert (Box 143)
      - WDF with John Conyers, Jr. (Box 143)
      - WDF with Hubert Humphrey (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Lyndon Johnson at bill signing (Box 143)
      - WDF with Robert F. Kennedy (Box 143)
      - WDF with Dean Rusk and cabinet member (?) Gronouski (Box 143)
      - WDF with Sargent Shriver (Box 143)
      - Trip to India taken as member of Education and Labor Committee (Box 143)
      - Trips to military posts, etc. (Box 143)
      - Municipal's Conference (Box 143)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 143)
    - 1966
      - WDF with HEW Secretary John Gardner (Box 143)
      - WDF with Speaker of the House John McCormack (Box 143)
      - Polish Millennium (Rose Garden ceremony) (Box 143)
      - Nominating petition filing, June 13 (Box 143)
    - 1967
      - With Gerald R. Ford and Spiro Agnew (Box 143)
      - Congressional baseball game (Box 143)
      - Political picnic (Box 143)
      - Campaigning with Robert Kennedy, G. Mennen Williams, and Zolton Ferency (Box 143)
    - 1968
      - Campaign (Box 143)
        (mainly with Hubert Humphrey)
      - Democratic National Convention (Box 143)
      - Michigan's Democratic congressional delegation (Box 143)
      - Political picnic (Box 143)
      - Tabulating questionnaire (Box 143)
      - School Officials Conference (Box 143)
        (mainly photos with Hubert Humphrey)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 143)
    - 1969
      - Political picnic (Box 143)
    - 1970
      - Receiving doctor of humane letters degree from Westfield State College (Box 143)
    - 1971
      - UAW convention 1971 (Box 143)
    - 1972
      - Campaign (Box 143)
        (filing petitions; awaiting election results)
      - WDF with James McNeeley at Democratic State Convention (Box 143)
      - WDF with Emanuel Celler (Box 143)
      - WDF campaigning with Sargent Shriver (Box 143)
    - 1973
      - WDF with Wilbur Cohen and Eloise Cohen (Box 143)
      - WDF with Rep. Daniel Flood and Thomas P. O'Neill (Box 143)
      - WDF at Gerald R. Ford vice presidential inaugural party (Box 143)
      - Kowalski sausage party with members of Michigan's congressional delegation (Box 143)
      - WDF with James Brickley and John Dingell (Box 143)
      - WDF speaking informally (Box 143)
    - 1974
      - Volunteers processing WDF's questionnaires (Box 143)
      - WDF listening to Nixon (Watergate) tapes (Box 143)
      - Reception for Gerald R. Ford as part of Man of the Year award (Box 143)
      - WDF with Jackie Onassis at political fund raising banquet (Box 143)
      - Brunner, Debbie (Photographer) (Box 143)
        (black and white photos taken showing WDF on floor of congress, in committee meetings, etc.)
    - 1975
      - Municipal Officials Conference (Box 143)
        (WDF with Senator Henry Jackson)
      - School lunch conference (Box 143)
      - WDF with Israel prime minister Rabin (Box 143)
      - Trip to the Middle East (Box 143)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 143)
    - 1976
      - Education and Labor Committee (Box 143)
      - Peruvian officials visit with WDF, Carl Albert, and others (Box 143)
      - WDF visit to Wayne County Intermediate School District (Box 143)
      - WDF with Congressmen Sarbanes and Brademus (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving Bicentennial Medal from John Warner (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree from Eastern Michigan University (Box 143)
    - 1977
      - WDF with President Jimmy Carter (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter at signing of Youth Employment and Demonstration Act (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter at signing of Juvenile Justice Act (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter at signing of Minimum Wage Act (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter aboard Air Force One (Box 143)
      - Committee hearings
        - Post and Civil Service (pay raise hearings) (Box 143)
        - Post secondary education, May (Box 143)
        - Post secondary education, June (Box 143)
        - Title I, State Migrant Program (Box 143)
        - Post secondary education (Box 143)
          (student loan defaults)
      - WDF with gas turbine car (Box 143)
      - WDF at School Officials Conference (Box 143)
        (with Joseph Califano and Ernest Boyer)
      - Political picnic (Box 143)
    - 1978
      - WDF with President Carter and others (Box 143)
        (re middle income college students financial aid)
      - WDF with President Carter at signing of Civil Service Reform Bill (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter at signing of Higher Education Act (Box 143)
      - WDF with Walter Mondale (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter and with the members of the Post Office and Civil Service Committee (Box 143)
      - WDF with other members of the Elementary and Secondary Education Act conference (Box 143)
      - Election night (Box 143)
    - 1979
      - Swearing-in ceremony, January 15 (Box 143)
      - Policy and Steering Committee meeting at the White House January 23, 1979 (Box 143)
      - Subcommittee trip to China, April (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree at Grand Valley State College (Box 143)
      - WDF at press conference regarding plant closing bill, July (Box 143)
      - WDF at reception honoring Joseph Califano (Box 143)
      - WDF at reception with Joan Mondale (Box 143)
    - 1980
      - WDF with President Carter, January (Box 143)
      - WDF with President Carter, February (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree at Wayne State University, March (Box 143)
      - WDF at Kennedy for President reception, April (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree at Northern Michigan University, April (Box 143)
      - WDF with Crystal Lee Sutton ("the real Norma Rae") (Box 143)
      - WDF at Speaker John McCormack's funeral, November (Box 143)
    - 1981
      - Mock swearing-in by Speaker Thomas P. O'Neill (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree at Central Michigan University, May (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree at the University of Detroit, May (Box 143)
      - Solidarity Day march, September (Box 143)
      - WDF receiving 33% from Freemasons (Box 143)
      - WDF with Claude Pepper, December (Box 143)
      - WDF (FIA?) with Coleman Young, John Dingell, and other public figures (Box 143)
    - 1982
      - WDF at commemoration of 100th birthday of Franklin Roosevelt (Box 143)
      - Post Secondary Education Subcommittee hearings, March (Box 143)
      - WDF and others discussing UAW-Ford Motor Company contract, March (Box 143)
      - WDF addressing steelworkers from McLouth Steel at rally in Washington D.C. (Box 143)
      - WDF and James Blanchard at Democratic State Convention, August (Box 143)
      - WDF at 20th anniversary reunion of members of the state constitutional convention (Box 143)
      - WDF and Ted Kennedy in Detroit, October (Box 143)
    - 1983 (Box 144)
      - General (Box 144)
        (include WDF receiving honorary degree from the U-M)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree from Cleary College (Box 144)
    - 1984
      - Dave Geiss, Sr. and Jr. (Box 144)
      - WDF receiving honorary degree from Northeastern University (Box 144)
      - Campaign rally with Walter Mondale and others, September 17, at Wayne Memorial High School (Box 144)
    - 1986
      - Campaign (WDF voting, etc.) (Box 144)
    - 1988
      - Political picnic (include Senator Donald S. Reigle) (Box 144)
      - Hatch Act rally (Box 144)
      - WDF with Governor Michael Dukakis, May 25 (Box 144)
      - Candidate Dukakis in Michigan, September-October (?) (Box 144)
    - 1989
      - WDF and members of Michigan's congressional delegation honoring the U-M basketball team, April (Box 144)
      - WDF and John Dingell, June (Box 144)
    - WDF at Vietnam War Memorial (honoring Freddy Heugel November 1990
      - Unveiling of WDF portrait, March 27 (Box 144)
      - WDF files nominating petition, May 7 (Box 144)
      - Airport noise hearings, September 25 (Box 144)
    - 1991
      - WDF with Queen Elizabeth, May (Box 144)
      - WDF and other members of Congress after passage of Civil Rights Bill, June (Box 144)
      - WDF with friends (Dingell, Jack Brooks, etc.) at hunting lodge, December (Box 144)
      - WDF and others at press conference regarding family and medical leave bill (1991 ?) (Box 144)
    - 1992
      - WDF speaking at OSHA reform rally (Box 144)
      - William Rehnquist testifying before WDF committee (1992 ?) (Box 144)
      - Michigan's congressional delegation, October (Box 144)
      - WDF campaigning with Senator Tom Harkin (Box 144)
      - WDF with Senator Dodd at press conference regarding family and medical leave bill, September (Box 144)
      - WDF campaigning at Ford Motor plant gate, October (Box 144)
      - WDF campaigning with Bill Clinton at Radisson in Ypsilanti, October 19 (Box 144)
      - WDF with Bill and Hillary Clinton (Box 144)
      - WDF and Ann Richards campaigning in Ann Arbor, October (Box 144)
        (Andrew Sacks, photographer)
      - WDF at Clinton campaign rally at Metropolitan Airport, November (Box 144)
    - 1993
      - WDF with Robert Reich (Secretary of Labor) (1993 ?) (Box 144)
      - WDF with Hillary Clinton, February 18 (Box 144)
      - WDF with Donna Shalala (Secretary of Health, Education and Welfare), March 3 and undated (Box 144)
      - WDF with Bill Clinton and committee chairs (Box 144)
      - WDF with Robert Reich and Congressman Bill Clay, May (Box 144)
      - WDF with Richard Riley, Secretary of Education (Box 144)
      - Hillary Rodham Clinton at Education and Labor committee hearing, September 29 (Box 144)
    - 1994
      - WDF as part of the Congressional delegation traveling to the funeral of House Speaker Thomas P. O'Neill (Box 144)
    - OVERSIZE PHOTOGRAPHS (in folder on top of other photos) (Box 144)
      (include autographed photos signed by Lyndon Johnson and Hubert Humphrey; also photos of WDF with Hubert Humphrey, Sargent Shriver, and President Lyndon Johnson)
  - Videotapes, 1987-1994
    Videotapes (VHS and U-matic) of Ford's monthly television program detailing events in Congress. Videotapes are arranged according to tape format. The tapes include campaign advertisements and television appearances by Ford.
    - Videotape reels [one inch] 1990-1992 (Box 145)
    - U-Matic Videotapes 1991-1993 (Box 146)
    - Betacam Videotapes 1990-1993 (Box 147)
    - VHS Videotapes 1987-1993 (Box 148)
    - VHS Videotapes 1991-1994 (Box 149)